All right בוקר טוב Boker Tov we pick up today on the
start with the last עמוד Amud of the eighth פרק, Perek, the
very top of נ"ג עמוד ב' Nun Gimmel Amud Bet and we're
still dealing with the בורא מאורי האש Borei Me'orei Ha'esh of הבדלה.
Havdalah. So it says אין מברכין על הנר עד שיאותו לאורו, Ein
Mevarchin al Ha'ner Ad She'ye'otu L'oro, very interesting הלכה Halacha that I
think the vast majority of people mistake. The הלכה Halacha is that
you do not make the ברכה Bracha until you derive benefit because
this ברכה Bracha on the נר Ner is not a ברכת הנהנין,
Birkat Ha'nehenin, evidence is you don't make it at other times during
the week, it's a ברכת השבח Birkat Ha'shevach as we mentioned the
other day, you have to acknowledge that now you're able to light
fire, you weren't on שבת Shabbos to distinguish like the fact of
הבדלה Havdalah between קודש Kodesh and חול, Chol, or this is because
on מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbos according to the מדרש Midrash אדם הראשון
Adam Ha'rishon created fire, beginning of the creative aspect of the week.
Anyway, so it is a ברכת השבח Birkat Ha'shevach and therefore you
do it after the experience, so you don't make the ברכה Bracha
on the fire until you derive benefit, not so and therefore you
know you're sort of looking at the fingers or whatever you're looking
at and then make the ברכה, Bracha, not the reverse. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says about this, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
לא יאותו יאותו ממש, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: Lo Ye'otu Ye'otu
Mamash, it doesn't mean you have to actually derive benefit אלא
כל שאילו עומד בקרוב ומשתמש לאורו, Ella Kol She'illu Omed Bikrov Umishtamesh
L'oro, as long as you're standing close enough that you could use
the light ואפילו בריחוק מקום Va'afillu Brichuk Makom and not only that
it's anybody who could, it's a good enough light that were somebody
standing they would be able to use it, then you can make
the ברכה Bracha even if you're at a distance, so you don't
even have to be in a position where you could use it,
but it has to be the type of light that could provide
light for to be used by somebody who would be standing close
enough to it. וכן אמר רב אשי בריחוק מקום, V'chen Amar Rav
Ashi: Brichuk Makom,
even if you're far away you could make the ברכה Bracha as
long as it has that ability, so two ideas: number one you
don't have to even be in that position, and number two certainly
you don't have to actually derive benefit, it just has to have
that quality. תנן Tnan מיתיבי Meitivei היה לו נר טמון בחיקו, Hayah
Lo Ner Tamun B'cheiko,
if you had a light hidden in your chest which is don't
get it too close but okay, presumably this does not just mean
a candle but maybe it means a lamp
או בפנס O Bifanas like a
lantern, או שראה שלהבת ולא נשתמש לאורה O She'ra'ah Shalhevet V'lo Nishtamesh
L'orah
or you saw flame and didn't use it או נשתמש לאורה ולא
ראה שלהבת O Nishtamesh L'orah V'lo Ra'ah Shalhevet
you used it without seeing it, אין מברך, Ein Mevarech, you can't
make the ברכה Bracha עד שיראה שלהבת וישתמש לאורה, Ad She'yir'eh Shalhevet
V'yishtamesh L'orah,
you have to both see the flame and use it. בשלמא נשתמש
לאורה
ולא ראה שלהבת, Bishlama Nishtamesh L'orah V'lo Ra'ah Shalhevet, I understand says
the גמרא Gemara the scenario where you could use it without seeing
it the flame, משכחת דקאי בקרנא דסביב Mishachka D'kami B'karna D'saviv
the flame is around the corner so you're getting the light and
but you're not able to use, but you're getting light but you
don't see the flame and you're able to use it. Yes, okay,
אלא ראה שלהבת
ולא נשתמש לאורה
היכי משתכחת
לה?
Ella Ra'ah Shalhevet V'lo Nishtamesh L'orah, Heichi
Mishtachach Lah?
But what's the reverse scenario that you saw the flame and didn't
use it, so it sounds like לאו דמרחק ליה, Lav D'merachak Lei,
doesn't it mean that you're far away? And even the גמרא Gemara
the simple scenario is you just didn't in practice use it, but
the גמרא Gemara is willing to say
at least it should mean you're not in the position to use
it, that you're far away. So the גמרא Gemara says לא דעמיא
ואזלא Lo D'amya V'azla no,
maybe being far away is okay, we're talking about that it's sort
of sputtering out and therefore because it's sputtering out you still see
some flame but the quality of the flame is not such that
anybody could use it even somebody who was close. So again notice
there are three possibilities here, one is you actually have to use
it which is the literal sense of the משנה, Mishna, one is
it has to have the ability to be used and you have
to be in a position to use it close enough, and the
גמרא Gemara goes all the way to the third thing which is
it has to have the ability to be used and you don't
even have to be in that close enough to use it you
can even be far away, and that's what the גמרא Gemara is
saying and the only thing excluded is when you can't see the
flame or when the flame doesn't have that quality, it's sputtering out,
and now we continue with that three lines down in the wide
lines, תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan גחלים לוחשות Gechalim Lochashot
if you have
smoldering embers, great translation, smoldering embers thank you, מברכין עליהן Mevarchin Aleihen
then you can make the ברכה, Bracha, עוממות Omimot
however לוחשות Lochashot is like it's actually a good like a whispering
like they're, you hear you know the flame is still going, however
עוממות Omimot if they are basically in the process of extinguishing, אין
מברכין עליהן Ein Mevarchin Aleihen
you can't because then presumably they're not in a position, they're not
strong enough that you could really use them. So the גמרא Gemara
says היכי דמי לוחשות? Heichi Dami Lochashot?
What would be an example of
לוחשות Lochashot whispering, אמר רב חסדא כל שאילו מכניס לתוכה קיסם ודולקת
מאליה, Amar Rav Chisda: Kol She'illu Machnis L'tocha Kisam V'doleket Me'eileha, if
you put in a wood chip and it lights on its own.
A little splinter, but if it wouldn't light up and you'd have
to stir it in order to so something else could catch, that
is not a strong enough flame. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they asked
the question: אוממות ommos with an א alef or עוממות ommos with
an ע? ayin? תא שמע, ta shema, דאמר רב חיסדא בר אבדימי:
de’amar Rav Chisda bar Avdimi: ארזים לא עממוהו בגן אלוהים. arazim lo
amamuhu be-gan elohim. So cedars which have not been, you know, somehow
burnt or whatever, extinguished in the, in the garden of God, so
that's with an ע, ayin, so presumably here
the גירסא girsa is with an ע. ayin.
So I wonder why they start דכשהן לוחשות מברכין עליהן אוממות dekeshehen
lochashos mevorchin aleihen ommos with an א. alef. Why are גירסאות? girsaos?
All right, so that's why the גמרא Gemara corrected it. ורבא אמר
יאותו ממש. ve-Rava amar ya’osu mamash. Rava says no, it's not enough
that you're far away, you have to actually literally derive benefit. Now,
even when he says ממש, mamash, he doesn't mean ממש, mamash, because
as we're going to see, it's going to be interpreted to mean
you have to be close enough that you could derive benefit, but
doesn't actually require the act of deriving benefit. How do I know
that? Let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues.
יאותו ya’osu means יבוא? yavo?
No, from the word נהנה. neheneh. יאותו... ya’osu... at least that's what
רש"י... Rashi... yeah, good, good.
Okay, that you derive benefit, right. Okay, הנאה hana’ah
seems to be, again, the verb made out of the word הנאה.
hana’ah. יהנה, yehaneh, I guess we would say, עד שיהנה. ad she-yehaneh.
But anyway, that's that's Rava. רש"י Rashi translates it as יהנה.
yehaneh. Okay, כמה?
kamma? How close, what... how strong of a flame is this? אמר
עולא: amar Ulla: כדי שיכיר בין איסר לפונדיון. kedei she-yakir bein issar
le-pundiyon. In order that it should be strong enough that you could
distinguish between, you know, an איסר issar and a פונדיון. pundiyon. We
would say, I don't know, a quarter and a nickel and a
nickel and a penny or something like that, a quarter and a
nickel. I mean, assuming that the sizes
weren't a strong enough... you know, weren't a good enough basis. חזקיה
אמר: Chizkiyah amar: כדי שיכיר בין מלוזמא של טבריא למלוזמא של ציפורי.
kedei she-yakir bein meluzma shel Tverya le-meluzma shel Tzipori.
In order that you could distinguish between a certain kind... a certain
type of a coin of Tiberias and the same type of coin
of Tzippori. So it has to be a strong enough strain you
could look at similar coins and distinguish their difference, something like that.
Now again, notice though that even when רבא Rava says ממש, mamash,
it's not being translated as ממש, mamash, it's being translated as כדי,
kedei, strong enough that you could do this, distinguish this way, but
again really it means probably just that you have to be close
enough. רש"י Rashi says ממש עומד בסמוך, mamash omed bisamuch, says רש"י.
Rashi.
Okay, someone said it's a weight. What?
It's a weight. Yeah, so weight or coin... right, it's a question.
רש"י Rashi says it's a weight, right, I thought it's a
coin. Okay. רב יהודה מברך עד בי אדא דיילא. Rav Yehuda mevarech
ad bei Ada Dayyala. Rav Yehuda made the ברכה bracha of, of...
of a flame that was in the house of אדא דיילא, Ada
Dayyala, which was somebody that was near him, that... that lived next
door, but he was still like not so close that he really
himself could have benefited from it. And the point is that רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda is going according to his פסק psak before that
even if you're far away you can make the ברכה. bracha. רבא
מברך עד בי גוריא בר חמא. Rava mevarech ad bei Gurya bar
Chama. Rava made a ברכה bracha on a flame he saw in
the house of גוריא בר חמא, Gurya bar Chama, which רש"י Rashi
says, again, this isn't in the גמרא, Gemara, but רש"י Rashi says
Rava having said a minute ago that you have to be close
enough to be able to derive benefit, this גוריא בר חמא Gurya
bar Chama lived close enough that if he wanted to, he could
have used his light. It's like, you know, what is it? Stealing
somebody else's wifi or whatever. If he wanted to, he could have
used the light. So it had windows. Yeah, well, yes, yes. אביי
מברך עד בי בר אבוה. Abaye mevarech ad bei bar Avuha. Okay,
and Abaye made a ברכה bracha on a flame he saw in...
בי בר אבוה. bei bar Avuha. So anyway, point is you can
be far away as long as it's a strong enough flame, at
least according to all the positions prior to רבא. Rava. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב: amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: אין מחזירין על האור.
ein machzirin al ha-or. A very important הלכה, halacha, also people aren't
aware of. I mean, not that it's bad that they're not aware
of this, but אין מחזירין על האור כדרך שמחזירין על המצוה. ein
machzirin al ha-or kederach she-machzirin al ha-mitzvah. You don't have to go
around looking for a candle if you don't have one easily available,
the same way if you have a מצוה mitzvah to do, you
have to like... you have to make sure that, you know, you
get your לולב. lulav. Or even more like, let's say, you know,
if you have to... you have to make sure you have wine
for קידוש. kiddush. You know, I mean... so clearly you don't have
wine for קידוש, kiddush, you go out, what do you do? You
buy wine. If you don't have wine then you knock at your
next-door neighbor's house, ask them if they have wine, you try to
find something else. If you don't have a candle for הבדלה, havdalah,
fine, skip it. Okay? You don't go to your next-door neighbor? Yeah,
you don't... what?
Not for שבת. Shabbos. Oh, for...
no, not for שבת. Shabbos. But that's a different conversation. We'll talk
about שבת Shabbos candles when we get to מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbos.
Correct. Let's take a look. אמר רב זירא: amar Rav Zeira: מרישא
הוה מהדרנא. me-reisha hava mihadarna. Originally I was looking around for some
candle to use for הבדלה. havdalah. כיון דשמענא להא דרב יהודה אמר
רב, keivan de-shamanah le-ha de-Rav Yehuda amar Rav, once I heard this
פסק, psak, אנא נמי לא מהדרנא. ana nami lo mihadarna. I also
don't even look around for it. אלא אם מקלע לי ממילא מברכינא.
ella im mikla li mi-meila mevarachina. If I happen to have a
candle, if I happen to find a light, then I'll make a
ברכה, bracha, but I don't go out of my way. Which is
quite fascinating. And by the way, obviously the next question is what
about בשמים? besamim? And the פוסקים poskim actually... כל
שכן בשמים. kol she-ken besamim. Because this is at least to symbolize
the difference between קודש kodesh and חול, chol, you know, to be
מכיר makkir that the The beginning of the creative week אדם הראשון
Adam HaRishon made fire and so on. בשמים besamim is just to,
like, for you, to restore you, like, you know, some, because you
lost your נשמה יתירה. Neshama Yeseira. So basically the הלכה halacha is
if you don't have בשמים, besamim, if you don't have a candle,
then okay, you make הבדלה havdala without it, you don't have to
drive yourself crazy. Yes.
Do the later commentaries talk about the שיעור shiur for the size
of the candle, even
quantifying in terms of number of lumens?
No. So I mentioned that yesterday,
the גמרא Gemara here does not mention a, what do you call
it, an אבוקה avuka at all, like a torch or whatever, you
know, multiple wicks. There is a גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim that
says that an אבוקה avuka is preferable, does not say required, first
of all. And even there there's a question, what is the point
of it? It might just be because it's a strong flame. The
whole idea that you דווקא davka need separate wicks, you know, and
we take two candles and put it together and that counts as
an אבוקה, avuka, you know, anyway that's sort of developed. But yes,
the גמרא Gemara earlier does say—the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim does
say that an אבוקה avuka is preferable. But beyond that, no, the
only discussion here about luminescence maybe to the degree that it's strong
enough that you could, you know, distinguish closely related things by its
light. Okay, but again a very interesting הלכה. halacha. I mean again,
it's not bad that people make a point of going and getting
it, it makes a much more nice הבדלה havdala ceremony. But, you
know, the question is how far does that even go? Like, let's
say when I'm in the store, when I'm in the store and
I'm shopping and I see a הבדלה havdala candle and I don't
have a הבדלה havdala candle at home, maybe I don't even have
to buy
it. Okay.
If I happened—yes. Is this a principle that's connected to the fact
that these are ברכות השבח? birchot hashevach?
That's an interesting point because and like I don't have to go
around looking for blossoming trees in order to make ברכת האילנות. birkat
ha-ilanot.
Is there any other ברכת השבח birkat hashevach that has a ritual
object connected to it?
Right, right. Well, that's also a good point that we turn the
flame, the הבדלה havdala candle, into a ritual object and ritualize even
the holder and so on. But the point that on the one
hand, I mean it also starts with the fact that הבדלה havdala
started as the הבדלה havdala in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Then, you
know, the גמרא Gemara says it moved to הבדלה על הכוס. havdala
al hakos. So even when it moved to הבדלה על הכוס, havdala
al hakos, it didn't mean you would have these other components. And
if the primary הבדלה havdala is in שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, it's
without these other components. So you make a good point that even
when we added these components, if fundamentally sort of they're not ברכת
המצווה, birchas hamitzvah, they're a type of ברכת השבח, birchas hashevach, then
that might also add to—well, you know, the בשמים besamim is more
ברכת הנהנין—but birchas hanehenin that might add to why they're not sort
of, you know, if you're in the store you hear the storm
you don't have to go chase it. Exactly, right. Right. No, I
hear it's a good point. I mean obviously they wanted to wrap
this up and it does become a question if I didn't make
it on the candle מוצאי שבת Motzaei Shabbos and I see a
flame later, right? Do I, you know, make the ברכה bracha later?
And you do. You know, you don't make it on the—question of
how far afterwards, but you could still make the ברכה bracha on
the flame even if you didn't have it immediately at the הבדלה
havdala ceremony. I mean, the מאורי האש Meorei Ha'esh would have been
like the two separate... I know, but as I'm saying, even in
the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim it was not clear and there's
different opinions and the גמרא Gemara concluded that it's preferable, but it's
not based on the מאורי האש. Meorei Ha'esh. מאורי האש Meorei Ha'esh
says בית הלל Beis Hillel because any flame has like different colors
to it. Okay. Is there also a parallel to the ברכה bracha
of אוזר ישראל בגבורה Ozer Yisrael bigvurah and עוטר ישראל בתפארה Atar
Yisrael betifarah on תשעה באב? Tisha B'av? It's customary to say in
the afternoon when you're wearing טלית ותפילין. tallis and tefillin. Right, that's
a ברכת השבח, birchas hashevach, right? Right. But you make it when
it happens later to the object of the טלית ותפילין, tallis and
tefillin, even though it's not really. Right. I think if memory serves
correctly that although you can make הבדלה havdala until Tuesday, that you
don't make מאורי האש Meorei Ha'esh after Saturday night, even if, you
know, if you—but you could make it if you didn't do it
during הבדלה, havdala, if you saw it later that evening, I think.
I don't remember exactly. Can you make it on a streetlight? So
that's an—so I mentioned yesterday that some פוסקים poskim when electric light
first came out, incandescent light, in order to make a point that
it was אש eish for שבת Shabbos and you couldn't use it
for שבת, Shabbos, made a point of using it for הבדלה havdala
and for saying בורא מאורי האש borei meorei ha-eish on those lights.
So again, I mean most people don't do that nowadays, but certainly
you'd be within your rights to do that. And then it's hard
to imagine that you would not actually see a light to make
one. I mean one must just—what the case is in the גמרא,
Gemara, what do you mean when I see a light? Well, were
they going around in the dark מוצאי שבת? Motzaei Shabbos? I mean
they had lights. So maybe, you know, so I don't know, I
don't know what the scenario was. Okay, it's—anyways, let's keep on going.
משנה. Mishna. Now, now on a different point—what? Do you use it
on a fluorescent? No, fluorescent nobody says that. Now the גמרא Gemara
goes on and totally—whatever, moving away from הבדלה. havdala. If you ate
and you forgot to בענטש bench and you left your place, so
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you have to go back in order
to בענטש bench and בית הלל Beis Hillel says you don't. I
should mention this is only about bread because bread you have the
idea of קביעות מקום. keviyas makom. That like, like there's a whole
idea you establish the place where you're eating and so on. but
by things like a שהכל shehakol or whatever, you don't have to,
there's no sense of a particular place of like you like you
establish, like you make your meal there. It's not considered a meal.
I'm always מזונות mezonos is the issue. Anyway, let's take a look.
So, אמר רב זביד ואיתימא רב דימי בר אבא, Amar Rav Zevid
ve-isayma Rav Dimi bar Abba, מחלוקת בשוכח, machlokes b'shoche'ach, the debate is
whether you have to go back if you forgot to bench. אבל
במזיד, Aval b'meizid, if you knew you had to bench and you
intentionally left the place
anyway because something more was pressing, דברי הכל יחזור למקומו, divrei hakol
yachzor limkomo, everybody requires you to go back ויברך v'yivareich and make
the ברכה. beracha. פשיטא, Pshita, says it's very obvious. בשוכח? B'shoche'ach? The
משנה mishna says you forgot. Now מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might
have thought הוא הדין אפילו במזיד, hu hadin afilu b'meizid, even intentional,
that בית הלל Beit Hillel says you do not have to go
back. והאי דקתני בשוכח? Ve-hai d'katani b'shoche'ach? Why do we say forgot?
להודיעך כוחן דבית שמאי, Le-hodi-acha kochan d'Beit Shammai, to teach me the
power of Beit Shammai's position, that they require you to go back
even בשוכח, b'shoche'ach, but maybe בית הלל Beit Hillel doesn't require even
במזיד. b'meizid. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that they're only debating
שוכח, shoche'ach, מזיד meizid even בית הלל Beit Hillel would agree. תניא,
Tanya, we learned in a ברייתא. braisa. אמרו להם בית הלל לבית
שמאי, Amru lahem Beit Hillel l'Beit Shammai, Beit Hillel said to Beit
Shammai, לדבריכם, l'divreichim, Beit Hillel says, what, how much are you requiring
these guys? According to you, מי שסעד בראש הבירה, mi she-sa-ad berosh
habira, somebody ate at the top of a tower ושכח, v'shachach, forgot
to bench, וירד, ve-yarad, and now he's at the bottom of the
tower, ולא בירך, v'lo beirach, and he forgot to bench. יחזור לראש
הבירה ויברך? Yachzor l'rosh habira v'yivareich? Do you want to make him
go all the way back up to the top in order to
bench? So how much do you want from this poor guy? So
אמרו להם בית שמאי לבית הלל, amru lahem Beit Shammai l'Beit Hillel,
Beit Shammai said to Beit Hillel, לדבריכם, l'divreichim, from what from your
position, מי ששכח ארנקי בראש הבירה, mi she-shachach arnaki b'rosh habira, let's
say he had forgotten his wallet at the top of the tower,
לא יעלה ויטלנה? lo ya'aleh v'yitlena? Would he not go up to
retrieve it? לכבוד עצמו הוא עולה, L'chvod atzmo hu oleh, he'd go
for his own sake, not exactly honor, but he'd go for his
own interest. לכבוד שמים לא כל שכן? L'chvod shamayim lo kol sheken?
How much more so should you retrieve for the sake of to
honor God if that is the proper place in which you should
bench is the place where you ate. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
has a story. הנהו תרי תלמידי חד עבד בשוגג כבית שמאי. Hanehu
trei talmidei chad avad b'shogeg k'Beit Shammai. Two students, one had a
scenario where he forgot
by mistake and he could have ruled like Beit Hillel, but he
was strict anyway and he went back like Beit Shammai to the
place where he had forgotten, where he had benched, where he had
eaten, ואשכח, v'ashkach, and when he went back to bench, what did
he find? ארנקי דדהבא. arnaki d'dahava. He found a wallet filled with
gold coins. So obviously playing on the previous theme of going back
for your wallet, this was his reward for listening to Beit Shammai.
He went back so much for God's honor that presumably not, he
went back so much for, he didn't have a סימן, siman, for
God's honor, that he found this stuff even for himself. וחד עבד
במזיד כבית הלל, V'chad avad b'meizid k'Beit Hillel, one intentionally left the
place and he didn't rule like Beit Hillel, Beit Hillel says intentionally
you have to go back, but was so unconcerned that he did
not go back even though he had left the place intentionally. ואכליה
אריה, Ve-achlei aryeh, and a lion ate him. And a lion then
benched. There's obviously an eating theme going on here. There's the wallet
and the eating. So you didn't care about where you ate, so
you were eaten anyway. Okay, now it's interesting of course because the
גמרא Gemara said before, you know if you remember by בית הלל
בית שמאי Beit Hillel Beit Shammai way back about saying שמע, Shema,
that בית שמאי Beit Shammai said that you're supposed to be reclining
when you say the nighttime שמע, Shema, and one person said, "Oh,
I was reclining and I endangered myself," and says "Oh, you got
what you deserved because you were פוסק paskening like בית שמאי." Beit
Shammai. Here clearly the גמרא Gemara feels like בית שמאי Beit Shammai
is an appropriate thing to be מחמיר machmir for and תוספות Tosafot
just says that explicitly. Even בית הלל Beit Hillel is not saying
you shouldn't do בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, he's just saying I'm not
demanding it from you. But clearly בית הלל Beit Hillel would agree
that that would be ideal. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, says
the following: רבה בר בר חנה הוה קאזיל בשיירתא. Rabbah bar bar
Chana hava ka-azil b'shayarta. Rabbah bar bar Chana was going on a
caravan. אכל, Achal, he ate, ואישתלי ולא בריך, v'ishtali v'lo beirach, and
he forgot and he didn't bench before the caravan moved on. אמר
היכי עביד, Amar heichi avid, what should I do? אי אמינא להו,
Ei amina lehu, if I tell the people driving the caravan, אנשאי
לברך, anshai l'varich, I forgot to bench, אמרי לי, amri li, they'll
tell me, בריך כל היכא דמברכת רחמנא מידכר, Berich kol heicha d'mevarchet
Rachmana midkar, bless wherever you are right now, wherever you're benching, you're
benching to God. God is everywhere. What do you want us to
do, stop so you can go back? God is everywhere, we just
don't need you to be in that place. So מוטב דאמינא להו,
mutav d'amina lehu, so here's what I'll do, I better I should
tell them the following: אנשאי יונה דדהבא, anshai yona d'dahava, I lost
a gold pigeon, like a gold, some type of an object made
out of gold, artistic object. אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said
to them, אמתינו לי דאנשאי יונה דדהבא, amtinu li d'anshai yona d'dahava,
wait for me, I left a gold pigeon back there. Maybe they
hadn't moved on yet, but they were ready to move on and
he said wait for me. אזיל וביריך, Azil v'beirach, he went and
he benched, ואשכח יונה דדהבא ve-ashkach yona d'dahava and lo and behold
he found this pigeon made out of gold, or whatever this dove
made out of gold. ומאי שנא יונה, U-mai shna yona, why did
he use that example? Or why is that what he was rewarded
with? דמתילי כנסת ישראל ליונה d'misli knesses yisrael l'yona because כנסת ישראל
knesses yisrael is compared to a dove. Dove, pigeon, דכתיב D'chtiv כנפי
יונה נחפה בכסף Kanfei yona nechpa b'chesef the wings of a dove
covered with silver ואברותיה בירקרק חרוץ V'evroteha b'yerakrak charutz or the feathers
of a dove covered with silver ואברותיה בירקרק חרוץ V'evroteha b'yerakrak charutz
and its wings with like a pure gold. So מה יונה אינה
ניצולת אלא בכנפיה. Ma yona eina nitzolat ela b'chnafha. Now we're going
to explain why we're compared to a dove. The same way a
dove is saved by its wings and its feathers, it flies away
if it's in trouble, אף ישראל אינם ניצולים אלא במצוות. Af Yisrael
einam nitzolim ela b'mitzvot. So we are saved by our performance of
מצוות. mitzvot. He was a מחמיר machmir on doing these מצוות mitzvot
and going back and so on. Again I really don't see exactly
the metaphor, but we do have doves other places, like the famous
case about the... who was it who was wearing תפילין tefillin and
then he... right and he... and he had to take them off
and he... you know, the Romans said you're not allowed to wear
תפילין tefillin and he said it's a dove and he opened his
hands and it was a dove. So that's a repeating theme. Anyway,
this is this idea about going back to where you're בענטשן benching
and what is the circumstances? How far do you have to go
back? The basic הלכה halacha is, well, okay, you know, let me
not get into the basic הלכה halacha because anyway, yes, go ahead.
Well, I mean, I know we've passed this, but it seems to
me that this is a מצווה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah ha-ba'ah b'aveirah. The
guy lied, you know. You know, I'm not getting into that, the
whole discussions about lying and white lies and whatever. The גמרא, Gemara,
it is not true that there's an absolute... that you can never
tell lies. Okay, but that's not... but I'm not getting into that,
exactly. Okay, Tully, you had a question? No, no. Right, let's talk
about sandwiches in our day. If you eat, if you start to
eat a sandwich, are you allowed to travel and then... so if
you move as... if you're eating as you're moving, then your קביעת
מקום kviyat makom is not limited to one place. And not only
that, if you have in mind that you're going to go somewhere
else, you could start in one place and plan to go somewhere
else, and so on. All of this is where you fully ate
in one place, you didn't have mind to go anywhere else, and
then you had to move or to continue somewhere else, and then
you, you know, and then you moved on. So then the question
of over going back. And again, שכח shachach you don't have to
go back, מזיד mezid you do. There's also questions about even in
a מזיד mezid scenario, obviously the extra point of the גמרא Gemara
is that even שכח shachach it's ideal to go back. And then
there's questions also like how far did... you know, at what... how
distant you have to be, how much out of your way, you
know, what's the... is there a limit to that? Yes. I want
to add to what Michael said. Not only did he lie, but
he made everybody wait for him in order for him to do
his ritual. That's a good point. And he delayed everyone. He knew
they'd be annoyed and that's why... right? Right. So was that what
we're supposed to take away from this? Well, you know what, that's
a good point. That's more of an issue than just the lying,
because, you know, white lies or whatever is... I mean, there's other
גמרות Gemarot about that that, you know, they're not so bad and
sometimes they're appropriate. But anyway, but that's not for our conversation now,
but the idea of being מטריח matriach people for something that isn't
הלכתית halachically required... right, right. That's a very good question. That... yeah,
that's a good point. One final point, though. Sorry. So even though
that we had this גמרא Gemara here that seems to clearly go
on the side of בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, we don't פוסק pasken
like him in this... Well, it inside it was talking about people
that were rewarded. But the גמרא Gemara earlier... No, that was because
it was מזיד. mezid. מזיד mezid even בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees.
But the guy was שוגג, shogeg, though, got back the הלכה. halacha.
Okay, so people were rewarded. It shows that it's ideal. It does
not show it's required. The גמרא Gemara earlier said we rule like...
if there was any doubt, we rule like בית הלל Beit Hillel
the whole פרק perek except for one case before. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues. עד אימתי, Ad eimatai, now here's another very relevant
הלכה. halacha. Until when are you still able to בענטשן bench if
it's been a while since you've eaten? So it says until the
food is digested. כמה שיעור עיכול? Kama shiur ikul? What is the
amount that food is digested? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל
זמן שאינו רעב, kol zman she-eino ra'ev, as long as you're no
longer not hungry. So you know, if you really went by that,
it could go for a few hours if the meal filled you
up and you don't start grazing in the fridge a minute later,
but okay, for some
people it's a few hours.
וריש לקיש אמר, V'Resh Lakish amar, כל זמן שיצמא מחמת אכילתו, kol
zman she-yitzma machmat achilato, as long as you're thirsty as
a result of your having eaten, which is interesting, which seems to
be a very small amount
of time, you know, assuming that they didn't drink so much during
the meal. So therefore, having eaten, now you're still want to have...
you know, you still need to be drinking because the meal is
still like
weighing you down or something.
It seems to be much less of a time.
Anyway, אמר ליה רב יימר בר שלמיא למר זוטרא, Amar lei Rav
Yeimar bar Shlamya l'Mar Zutra, ואמרי לה רב יימר בר שיזבי למר
זוטרא, v'amri lah Rav Yeimar bar Shizbi l'Mar Zutra, so one of
them said to מר זוטרא, Mar Zutra, מי אמר ריש לקיש הכי?
Mi amar Resh Lakish hachi? Did ריש לקיש Resh Lakish really say
this? והאמר רב אמי אמר ריש לקיש, V'ha-amar Rav Ami amar Resh
Lakish, כמה שיעור עיכול? kama shiur ikul? What is the amount of
digestion? כדי להלך ארבעה מילין, kdei lehalech arba'ah milin, the time it
takes to walk four מיל. mil. So the גמרא Gemara says, which
is 72 minutes. Well, not exactly clear, which is longer. ולא קשיא,
V'la kashya, כאן באכילה מרובה כאן באכילה מועטת, kan b'achila meruba kan
b'achila mu'etet, whether it's a big meal or a small meal. So
the debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. רש״י Rashi says a
big meal is four מיל, mil, a small meal is less and
it's this thirsty idea. תוספות Tosafot says the reverse. תוספות Tosafot thinks
the thirsty can last a while, but anyway, the real הלכה halacha
is like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it's until it gets digested...
I mean until you're full... because the גמרא Gemara gives this quantifiable
amount of four מיל, mil, four מיל mil is 72 minutes. I
mean actually there's a debate how long it takes to walk a
מיל. mil. anything from 18 to 24 minutes, but the pretty much
consensus is 18 minutes.
So four מיל mil is 72 minutes. So therefore the general rule
is that you don't בענטש bentch 72 minutes after having eaten.
What some people do is they'll like nibble a little bit every
72 minutes to extend the time, but you know there is some
but yeah, but there is some question because the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say say you know says doesn't exactly identify those, and it might
in the end be if you really are full even more than
72 minutes so it raises some questions about that. All right, let's
continue. בא להם יין. Ba lahem yayin. Now, here's very important הלכה
halacha about about saying אמן. Amen. So the גמרא Gemara says it
skip it jumps to the very end which is you say אמן
Amen after a ישראל Yisrael whose ברכה bracha you did not hear
the whole thing but not after a כותי Kuti because you are
concerned about whether who to whom he made the ברכה, bracha, whether
it was to God or to עבודה זרה avoda zara or whatever.
So it's only if you hear the whole ברכה. bracha. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: למימרא דישראל אף על גב דלא שמע
כולה ברכה עונה? Lemaimra deYisrael af al gav dalo shama kula bracha
oneh? It sounds like a ישראל Yisrael even if you heard a
ברכה bracha from a ישראל Yisrael even if you didn't hear the
whole ברכה bracha you say אמן. Amen. So the גמרא Gemara says
how could that be? וכי לא שמע היכי נפיק? Vechilo shama heichi
nafik? If you didn't hear the whole ברכה bracha how can you
be יוצא? yotzei? It assumes you have to hear the whole ברכה
bracha in order to be יוצא. yotzei. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר חייא בר רב בשלא אכל עמהן. Amar Chiyya bar Rav beshelo
achal imahen. No, you didn't eat with them so you don't need
to be יוצא, yotzei, you're not יוצא בענטשינג. yotzei bentching. It's just
about הלכה halacha about saying אמן, Amen, it's not הלכה halacha about
being יוצא. yotzei. To be יוצא yotzei you have to hear the
whole ברכה. bracha. Okay now before we go on, I should say
that this is a very important הלכה halacha because you know very
often people will hear קידוש, Kiddush, miss some words, you know or
hear I mean קידוש Kiddush is you're being יוצא, yotzei, you're normally
not being יוצא yotzei by בענטשינג bentching and say אמן Amen and
according to this גמרא Gemara and this is the way it's ruled
in שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, you have to hear every single word
in order to be יוצא. yotzei. So you know and then it
also becomes an issue that everybody starts singing along, והנחילנו בשמחה ve'hinchilanu
b'simcha and then you're not I maybe you're not hearing the the
person actually who you're being יוצא yotzei through. Okay so, interesting, can
you combine hearing one person's voice and another person's voice? Anyway, it
raises real issues about hearing the whole ברכה. bracha. Now the רמב"ם
Rambam interestingly says the following. The רמב"ם Rambam says כל השומע ברכה
מתחלה ועד סוף הרי זה... kol hashumea bracha mitechila ve'ad sof harei
zeh... no it says like, no it says like this: כל העונה
אמן הרי זה כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי. Kol ha'oneh Amen harei zeh
kemotzi bracha mipiv dami. If you say אמן Amen it's like you
said the ברכה bracha directly, it came out of your mouth, the
word אמן Amen ditto is like the wrapped up entire ברכה bracha
in that one word, כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי. kemotzi bracha mipiv dami.
וכל השומע ברכה מתחלה ועד סוף אף על פי שלא ענה אמן
הרי זה כאילו ענה אמן vechol hashumea bracha mitechila ve'ad sof af
al pi shelo ana Amen harei zeh k'ilu ana Amen or something
like that. Okay so if you heard it from beginning to end
even if you didn't say anything you just heard it it's like
you said אמן. Amen. So from the simple structure of the רמב"ם
Rambam it says like when you say אמן Amen that actually is
like you said the whole ברכה bracha even if you didn't hear
the whole thing because that word sort of symbolizes the whole ברכה.
bracha. And only if you didn't say אמן Amen do you have
to hear it from beginning to end. So the כסף משנה Kessef
Mishneh who's the בית יוסף Beis Yosef acknowledges that that's פשט pshat
in the רמב"ם, Rambam, but he based on this גמרא Gemara he
says you can't read it that way because this גמרא Gemara said
how could you be יוצא yotzei if you didn't hear the whole
ברכה bracha even though you said אמן? Amen? So although from the
רמב"ם Rambam it sounds like saying אמן Amen you don't have to
hear the whole ברכה, bracha, the הלכה halacha is not that way.
So it's actually something that people have to be very careful about
because it's very common that people really don't hear the whole ברכה.
bracha. Okay now you could say maybe if you didn't hear a
word that other even if you didn't hear it you would be
יוצא, yotzei, like you were saying the whole קידוש, Kiddush, right, you
know and I missed a few words in the middle, but I
heard the ברכה bracha I heard the core at the beginning and
the core at the end or whatever, fine, that's a different story.
But if you missed a key part of it, that's a real
issue and something that people really have to be מקפיד makpid on
Friday night. Friday night. Yeah, שבת, Shabbos, no, שבת Shabbos the whole
קידוש Kiddush is דאורייתא, d'oraysa, I get that, right, right. But when
you're being יוצא, yotzei, right and the Friday night also the the
first paragraph יום הששי ויכלו Yom HaShishi Vayechulu whatever is also not
the core ברכה. bracha. But when you're being יוצא yotzei you do
have to hear really hear the words of the ברכה bracha that
you're being יוצא yotzei with. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara goes
on, וכן אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה בשלא אכל עמהן.
Vechen amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha beshelo achal imahen. No,
we're talking about saying אמן Amen and you're not being יוצא yotzei
and therefore you don't have to hear the whole ברכה. bracha. אמר
ליה רב לחייא בריה. Amar lei Rav leChiyya brei. So רב Rav
said to חייא's Chiyya son, בריה brei my son, חטוף ובריך, Chatof
u'vrich, grab and bless, meaning you should be the one that jumps
to the opportunity to lead the בענטשינג bentching or to say a
ברכה bracha for a group. וכן אמר רב הונא לרבה בריה חטוף
ובריך, Vechen amar Rav Huna leRabbah brei chatof u'vrich, grab and בענטש.
bentch. So למימרא דמברך עדיף ממאן דעני אמן? Lemaimra demivarech adif miman
de'ani Amen? That sounds like the one who makes the ברכה bracha
is better than saying אמן. Amen. והתניא דתניא רבי יוסי אומר גדול
העונה אמן יותר מן המברך, Vehatanya detanya Rabbi Yossi omer gadol ha'oneh
Amen yoter min hamivarech, the one who says אמן Amen is better
than the one who's makes the ברכה. bracha. So אמר ליה רבי
נהוראי, Amar lei Rabbi Nehorai, so רבי נהוראי Rabbi Nehorai says I'll
tell you השמים, Hashamayim, by heaven this is true, כן הוא. ken
hu. תדע, Teda, you should know, שהרי גויירין יורדין ומתגרין, sheharei goyarin
yordin umitgarin, the soldiers, infantrymen go down and they sort of clash
and you know make the initial wars, they're the ones that go
out in the front במלחמה, bemilchama, וגבורים יורדין ומנצחין, vegiborin yordin umenatzchin,
and after that then the the mighty ones go down and win.
come in and they roll in with the tanks and they're the
ones that actually win the victory. So therefore, the person that goes
first is not the one that wins the victory, it's the one
that says אמן. Amen. So, a way of thinking about this I
saw in interesting people know this thing TED talks, I never watched
them, but somebody, somebody showed me one of them which was very
good, which was about the importance of being a follower. It says,
you know, we always hear about leadership training, importance of being a
leader. It says one guy goes out there, he's a leader, and
nobody follows him, he's a kook. The real important person is the
person that comes afterwards and follows him and makes it sort of
signals to other people that it's okay, that you know that he
should be followed, and you know so these are the followers of
the people that are you know the initial followers are playing just
as key of a role as leaders and they normally that the
importance of that is often ignored. But anyway, so that's a certain
sense, you make a ברכה, bracha, bless this guy or whatever. Maybe
that's you're the only one, we all think you're crazy. You start
saying אמן, Amen, you show that there are other people that actually
are, you know, share in this acknowledgment, that there's a real power
to that idea that you're not a loner but this is something
communally acknowledged. Yes, this line is written in gigantic letters on the
walls of the אלטנוישול Altenneuschul in Prague from the 12th century, ostensibly
because it meant גדול העונה אמן. Gadol ha'oneh amen. So they're not
talking during the דאוונען. davening. Oh I see. Right, right, okay, strictly
probably right. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says תנאי. Tannai. So
what do you do? One says it's better to say אמן Amen
and the other says it's better to lead. So it's a debate
of תנאים, Tannaim, תניא, Tanya, it's taught in a ברייתא, Braita, אחד
המברך ואחד העונה אמן במשמע, echad hamivarech ve'echad ha'oneh amen bamashma, both
bless, the one who makes the blessing and the one who says
אמן Amen are like equivalent, אלא שממהרים למברך יותר מן העונה, ella
shememaharim lamivarech yoter min ha'oneh, you go quicker to the blesser than
to the one who responds. What does that mean? It means that
the heaven rewards more quickly the one who makes the ברכה bracha
than the one who responds. So anyway, there's a debate of תנאים,
Tannaim, so here's saying be of the one who makes the blessing.
Normally of course that's the assumption we make, that you give an
honor to the one who's leading, but it is a very important
concept about the importance of responding, being an equal part in the
ceremony and you know equivalent or maybe even better. It's not all
about the one making the ברכה. bracha. Now again, this is a
different question from the one we had before, which is, is it
better for each one to make their own ברכה bracha or to
be part of a congregation, you know, part of one person lead
and other people answer אמן. Amen. You could have said if you
say being the מברך mivarech is better then everybody should be their
own מברך. mivarech. But not necessarily. The גמרא Gemara before said, you
know, that the idea of ברוב עם, berov am, there's a power
of, fine, maybe you should try to be the one מברך, mivarech,
but the ideal of it is to have one מברך mivarech and
everybody else responds, not have everybody going off on their own. And
that's generally what we assume, that the ברוב עם berov am is
better than everybody breaking up and doing their own ברכה. bracha. Not
to mention what? What did you say? Yeah, but but right, okay,
yes, that's true. But that has to do with the fact that
בענטשן bentschen is about הנאה hana'ah or whatever as opposed to מצוות.
mitzvot. Yes. If we didn't have the additional commentary, doesn't the first
comment sound like any parent talking to any child to say, but
you should be the leader in your group and get them to
do the right thing? Could be. Right, that's true. That is true.
Does this mean that when you're at someone's house for שבת Shabbat
and the בעל הבית ba'al habayit makes קידוש, Kiddush, right, and says
would anybody else like to make their own קידוש Kiddush and and
people start making their own קידוש, Kiddush, here it sounds it would
be preferable to say no, I'm going to be יוצא yotzei with
the קידוש... Kiddush... well, no, that's not clear here. Here it's not
clear. Here it says if you have to choose between מברך mivarech
and עונה אמן, oneh amen, there's a question and maybe in the
end you choose מברך, mivarech, you might have come to the conclusion
better I should make my own ברכה bracha rather than being עונה
אמן oneh amen to you, but that's a separate as I said
that's a separate issue and that came up before about the ברוב
עם berov am idea versus you know and in the end we
you know there are some ראשונים Rishonim that do say that and
that's why there are some people who prefer to make their own
קידוש. Kiddush. But you know overwhelmingly we assume no, the ברוב עם
berov am is better, so don't sort of break up the group,
be part of the group. But once you have that group and
one person is leading, then the question is which is better. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, בעי מיניה שמואל מרב. Ba'ei
minei Shmuel meRav. שמואל Shmuel asked from רב, Rav, מהו לענות אמן
אחר תינוקות של בית רבן? mahu la'anot amen achar tinokot shel beit
raban? How about kids that are learning to make ברכות brachot and
they're not being יוצא, yotzei, they're just making ברכות brachot out of
practice? Should you say אמן? Amen? Because the ברכה bracha in its
context is not a real ברכה, bracha, it's just practice. So אמר
לו אחר הכל עונים אמן חוץ מתינוקות של בית רבן. amar lo
achar hakol onim amen chutz mitinokot shel beit raban. No, you answer
אמן Amen after anybody's ברכה bracha except this, this is not a
real ברכה, bracha, this is just practice, הואיל וללמוד עשויין, ho'il ulelamed
asuyin, they're only doing it for practice. והני מילי בדלא עידן מפטירייהו.
Vehani mili bidlo idan maftirayhu. That's not at the time of מפטירייהו.
maftirayhu. What does that mean? רש״י Rashi says it means when they're
getting the הפטרה, Haftarah, because they used to give minors the הפטרה.
Haftarah. And then it really is a ברכה bracha that's meaningful. The
ראב״ד Ra'avad says that it means when they're being פוטר poter themselves,
when they're being יוצא. yotzei. So when they're not practicing, even if
they're a kid, but if they're making a ברכה bracha before eating
an apple, or before taking a לולב lulav or something, you do
answer אמן, Amen, because then it does have the right context. השתא
מיהא? Hashta miha? No, I'm saying השתא מיהא, hashta miha, you're not
being יוצא yotzei because they're kids still, אבל בעידן מפטירייהו aval be'idan
maftirayhu when they're being יוצא. yotzei. with it, and we did it
the דאורייתא d'oraissa way, and it's not just practice, אמן amen you
would answer. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, that's how we rule. Say ברוך
אתה. Baruch Atah. Yeah, they would give the הפטרה haftarah even in
the time to them to say אמן amen even if... Because women,
it's a whole issue whether women can say the ברכות brachot before
the הפטרה haftarah and women... so this would say... Well, yeah, I
mean, that's not always... I mean, it comes up from all discussion
in מגילה Megillah and so on, but yes, based on the גמרא
Gemara and the practice even through the Middle Ages, go, well, I
don't know about women, but the practice was to give minors the
הפטרה. haftarah. So why not? Yeah, okay. That's true. That's exactly what's
discussed. I understand, I'm not going to give you answer right now,
but yes, that is exactly the comparison that is made. Yes, that
is exactly the parallel that is made. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay.
שמן מעכב את הברכה, Shemen me'akeiv es habracha, דברי רבי זילאי. divrei
Reb Zilai. So wrapping up... it's why... yeah, I know, wiping your
hands with oil... with the way they did it at the end
of the meal to get off the, you know, because we had
talked before at the end of this משנה mishna was about מים
אחרונים, mayim acharonim, so we're jumping back to that. Or, you know,
so, with, with oil to get off the smell, then if you,
before you do that, you can't bench. You have to clean your
hands first. רב זיבאי אמר, Rav Zivai amar, רב זיבאי Rav Zivai
says, אינו מעכב. eino me'akeiv. No, it doesn't. רב אחא אמר, Rav
Acha amar, שמן טוב מעכב. shemen tov me'akeiv. If you normally have
good smell, aromatic oil, then you need to do that, if that's
your practice, as רש"י Rashi says, before you bench. רב זוהמי אומר,
Rav Zuhmai omer, which is interesting... זוהמא zuhma means your normal stench
anyway... רב זוהמי Rav Zuhmai says, right, כשם שמזוהם... kesheim shemezuham... no,
זוהמי מזוהם, Zuhmai mezuham, maybe he was named after... because of this
statement... in the same way, a כהן Kohen who is מזוהם, mezuham,
smelly, פסול לעבודה, pasul l'avodah, cannot work, כך ידיים מזוהמות פסולות לברכה,
kach yadayim mezuhamot pesulot l'bracha, when your hands are smelly, you cannot
bench the ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אנא לא זילאי ולא זיבאי ולא זוהמי ידענא.
Ana lo Zilai v'lo Zivai v'lo Zuhmai yadana. I don't know these
guys: זילאי, Zilai, זיבאי, Zivai, זוהמי. Zuhmai. Who ever heard of them?
אלא מתניתא ידענא. Ella masnisa yadana. Meaning, I don't, you know, whatever
they're saying, I don't know where it's coming from. Here's what I
know. I got a ברייתא. braisa. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, D'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav, ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא. v'amri lah bemasnisa tana.
Says in the name of רב, Rav, or some say taught in
the ברייתא: braisa: והתקדשתם והייתם קדושים. v'hiskadishtem v'hiyisem kedoshim. Sanctify yourselves and
be holy. והתקדשתם אלו מים ראשונים, V'hiskadishtem eilu mayim rishonim, washing hands
before the meal. והייתם קדושים אלו מים אחרונים. V'hiyisem kedoshim eilu mayim
acharonim. And then you make yourselves holy, that is the water at
the end. Both ways in which we sort of, sense of holiness,
that purity and holiness associated with washing hands. כי קדוש זה שמן.
Ki kadosh zeh shemen. אני ה' אלוהיכם זו ברכה. Ani Hashem Elokeichem
zu bracha. So, I don't know, the קדוש, kadosh, the third קדוש
kadosh is three ways of cleanliness, you know, cleanliness is next to
godliness. So three קדושים kedoshim in that פסוק. pasuk. Water at the
beginning, water at the end, the oil following it, and then you
say השם's Hashem name, then you make the ברכה. bracha. Okay, so
this is yet another source for this idea of מים אחרונים mayim
acharonim that תוספות Tosafos of course says, you know, this is only...
the גמרא Gemara says that if you're not, if you don't normally
have שמן shemen to wash your hands, that's not required. So he
says for us, we normally don't use, you know, we normally don't
have מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim, so therefore we don't have to worry
about it. And, you know, that gets to the whole discussion of
why we don't have מים אחרונים mayim acharonim nowadays. It is, however,
a different emphasis on what the idea of מים אחרונים mayim acharonim
is, where other גמרות Gemoras emphasize מלח סדומית, melach sdomis, which is
a health concern, this sort of sees it as more of a
ritual idea, the washing of the hands. The שמן shemen might be
a smelliness issue, but the water at least seems to be possibly
connected to more of a ritual. Maybe not, maybe it's the cleanliness
is connected to the קדושה, kedusha, like by the idea of the
שמן. shemen. But anyway, this is another source for מים אחרונים mayim
acharonim and the question about whether we do or don't do it
nowadays if these are not our issues. I for a while thought,
I still think it's a good theory, although I can't prove, although
I don't think the facts back it up, is that the reason
תוספות Tosafos said that מים mayim they didn't bother with the water
in his days was because of the invention of forks and the
widespread use of forks. The whole problem was was that you handled
the food with your hands, right? And the... for the meat was
very salty, and that was the מלח סדומית, melach sdomis, you know,
before spray, whatever, became a thing in the Middle Ages, and then
your hands didn't get dirty. Problem is that I think that the
forks came a century after תוספות Tosafos said we don't worry about
the מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. So anyway, I'm still working on that
one. I wonder whether or not in Mediterranean countries they did not
use cutlery the way they did in Northern Europe. They still used
their hands and מים אחרונים mayim acharonim is very widespread in ספרד.
Sefard. Oh, that's interesting. That's interesting. Right, I said the only problem
with that theory is that I think that תוספות Tosafos is saying
in the twelfth century and I think that the cutlery spread in
the thirteenth century. So I don't know, may have to research that
one further. It's a good theory, even if it's not true. There's
also this דרשה drasha at the end and even in the סדר
העבודה, Seder Ha'avodah, if I'm not mistaken, the verb קידש kideish means
to wash with water. Oh, that's true. That's a good point also.
טאקע, Taka, that's very true. Right, קידוש ידים ורגלים kiddush yadayim v'raglayim
is what we call the washing of the... Right. So this is
not so farfetched, it's just a parsing of the three or four
appearances of the verb קידש. kideish. Right, right, is it in the
תורה Torah or is that just how it's referred to in the
תנאי Tannaitic literature? The קידוש... kiddush... קידוש ידים ורגלים Kiddush yadayim v'raglayim
I think is Tannaitic, I don't think it's, I don't think it's,
yeah, פסוק. pasuk. No, but I understand, but I'm saying it's self-referential
once within the Tannaitic literature we call washing hands קידוש ידים Kiddush
yadayim then it would have right. I don't... okay, yeah, that's a
good point. שפיר קאמרת. Shapir ka'amarta. Yes, Charlie, right, right, right. The
personal table fork most likely originated in the Eastern Roman or Byzantine
Empire, spread through the Middle East in the first millennium CE, and
then spread into Southern Europe during the second millennium. It did not
become common in Northern Europe until the 18th century, not coming to
North America until the 19th century. Okay, so anyway, it's possible, it's
possible it was already there at the time of the תוספות. Tosafot.
All right, refers... required... not clear... requires greater research. I will say
one final thing about saying אמן, amen, which is this גמרא Gemara
speaks about saying אמן, amen, not saying אמן amen to a כותי
Kuti until you hear the whole ברכה, bracha, and the שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch brings down also not saying אמן amen to a ברכה
bracha of an אפיקורוס, epikoros, and there's a discussion in the פוסקים
poskim about even is it even if you hear the whole ברכה
bracha of an אפיקורוס, epikoros, or if you don't hear, like maybe
even if you hear the whole ברכה bracha you don't know what
he's thinking about it or whatever. First of all, everybody says I
should say that you do say אמן amen to a ברכה bracha
of a גוי. goy. Yeah, if you hear the whole ברכה. bracha.
And there are even the ראשונים Rishonim even say even though what
the גוי goy says God, they're thinking of a different God concept
than our God concept, nevertheless they're blessing God and there's enough sense
of a same shared idea of God even though their idea is
different that you would say אמן amen to the ברכה bracha of
a non-Jew. That is assumed. And that's actually even פסק. paskened. The
question is about the ברכה bracha of an אפיקורוס, epikoros, if you
hear the whole ברכה bracha and he says God, can you trust
enough what that word means for the אפיקורוס? epikoros? The אפיקורוס epikoros
is more of a discussion than the גוי. goy. And I mentioned
this because there's some very challenging פסקים psakim of Rav Moshe Feinstein
of saying not answering אמן amen to the ברכה bracha of a
Conservative or Reform Jew because he says he doesn't mean anything when
he says God, which is shocking. Like in another place he speaks
about a ברכה ברכת התורה bracha Birkat HaTorah where you know question
is if they don't actually believe that the תורה Torah is from
God and so on can make the ברכת התורה. Birkat HaTorah. But
he says even a normal ברכה bracha he says you know it's
just he doesn't believe in God which is I don't know why
he's making that assumption. It's a very... but a couple of תשובות
tshuvot Rav Moshe Feinstein says that very challenging. Yes. Christians will often
end blessings with in you know who's name. Yes, I don't think
we're not referring to that. We're referring to they said God but
their concept of God is different. Okay. You know the history of
עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? What? Yeah, yes, that's why I mentioned it.
I'm not getting into that, you can think about that. And with
that there's פרק הדרן עלך אלו דברים. perek Hadran alach elu devarim.
Let's start now the next פרק. perek. Okay. So now we move
on.